Guide to the William H. Helfand Collection of Medical Prints and Posters, 1695-1991, bulk 1800-1899
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
William H. Helfand Collection of Medical Prints and Posters 1695-1991, bulk 1800-1899
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Helfand, William, H.
3.0 linear feet Extent: 34 Items
William Helfand is a scholar of pharmaceutical history and art, and collector of ephemera and art related to medicine. The William H. Helfand Collection of Medical Prints and Posters consists of 34 prints and posters realted to the history of medicine and pharmacology, dating from 1695 to 1991, with the bulk of the prints dating from 19th century. Paris, France is the provenance for many of the posters, but several hail from England and the United States. The posters are represented in two formats: lithographs and engravings, some of which are hand colored. Ranging in size from 5"x8" to 19"x23", the prints include caricatures, political satire, comics and advertisements, dealing with a range of subjects from quacks, alchemy, charlatans and cheats, to pastoral and hospital scenes. George Cruikshank and Honoré Daumier are represented amongst the artists. Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
RL.00550
Language: Material in English and French
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The William H. Helfand Collection of Medical Prints and Posters were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2012.
Biographical Note
William H. Helfand has a degrees in Chemical Engineering, Pharmacy and was awarded degrees of Doctor of Humane Letters and Doctor of Science. His many written works include Pharmacy: An Illustrated History, The Picture of Health, articles on medical and pharmaceutical prints, posters, and ephemera. In the mid-1950s, Helfand began collecting medical prints and posters, many of which have been exhibited at the National Library of Medicine and Philadelphia Museum of Art, amongst others. He is currently an art and medicine consultant to the National Library of Medicine and the Philadelphia Museum of Art.
Collection Overview
The William H. Helfand Collection of Medical Prints and Posters consists of 34 prints and posters realted to the history of medicine and pharmacology, dating from 1695 to 1991, with the bulk of the prints dating from 19th century. Paris, France is the provenance for many of the posters, but several hail from England and the United States. The posters are represented in two formats: lithographs and engravings, some of which are hand colored. Ranging in size from 5"x8" to 19"x23", the prints include caricatures, political satire, comics and advertisements, dealing with a range of subjects from quacks, alchemy, charlatans and cheats to pastoral and hospital scenes. George Cruikshank and Honoré Daumier are represented amongst the artists. Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Cruikshank, George, 1792-1878; Daumier, Honoré, 1808-1879; Helfand, William H. [collector]; Advertising -- Drugs; Medicine and art; Medicine -- History; Medicine-- Posters; Medicine -- Practice -- England; Medicine -- Practice -- France; Medicine -- Practice -- United States; Pharmacy -- History; Pharmacy -- Posters; Quacks and quackery in art; Caricatures; Engravings; Lithographs; Posters; Prints; History of Medicine Collections (Duke University)
Related Material
Collection of Albert Cornell, M.D., 1938-2004 [medical and pharmaceutical advertising ephemera]
Rubenstein Library, Duke University
William H. Helfand Collection of Advertising Postcards, 1978-2000 and undated [also contains 5 papers by Helfand on medical and pharmaceutical advertising]
Rubenstein Library, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- William H. Helfand Collection of Medical Prints and Posters, 1695-1991, bulk 1800-1899, (3 boxes)
  The medical prints and posters are arranged alphabetically by author. The prints are lithographs or engravings, with some in color. Titles are taken from the items.
  - Anonymous, I've got the rumatiz, U.S., 1914, (lithograph) (Box 1)
  - Anonymous, Malade imaginaire holding cane with nurse, Paris, 1888, (engraving) (Box 1)
  - Anonymous, Nun pouring dose for seated girl, Paris, circa 1875, (lithograph) (Box 1)
  - Anonymous, The out-door girl, advertisement for Hood's Sarsparilla, circa 1885, (color lithograph) (Box 1)
  - Anonymous, The quack doctor, U.S., circa 1865, (lithograph) (Box 1)
  - Anonymous, Reméde Universel, Paris, circa 1789, (hand-colored engraving) (Box 2)
  - Anonymous, La visite a l'hopital nouvelle tenue des infirmières, Paris, 1904, (color lithograph) (Box 2)
  - Alexandre, Colin, Duo de seringues à baton mécanique entre deux époux dumarais Martinet, Paris, 1823 [caricature], (hand-colored lithograph) (Box 1)
  - Bourdel, Ma fortune est faite! J'ai trouvé une poudre à canon imperméable et incombustible, Paris, circa 1845 [satiric cartoon of scientist's laboratory], (hand-colored lithograph) (Box 2)
  - Chéret, Jules, Kola marque, Paris, circa 1895, (color lithograph) (Box 3)
  - Cillorse (?), Une cure merveilleuse, Paris, circa 1875, (color lithograph) (Box 1)
  - Coe, Sue, Just say no to hormone milk, U.S., 1991, (lithograph) (Box 1)
  - Cruikshank, George, The fox and the goose, London, 1833, (lithograph) (Box 1)
  - Daumier, Honoré, Mon Dieu! M'ame Bombec, qué que vous avez donc attrapé?... Paris, 1861 [satire in newsprint], (lithograph) (Box 2)
  - Daumier, Honoré, Robert Macaire Medecin, Paris, 1836 [satire in newsprint], (hand-colored lithograph) (Box 2)
  - Dusort, Cornelis, Kopster, Holland, 1695 [bloodletting], (engraving) (Box 1)
  - Gibele after Melling, Éstablissement thermal de Barèges, Paris, circa 1850, (color lithograph) (Box 3)
  - Gillray, James, Britannia between death and the doctors, London, 1804, (hand-colored engraving) (Box 2)
  - Grandville and Forest, Memento homo quia pulvis et in pulverem reverteris, Paris, 1833 [caricature], (hand-colored lithograph) (Box 2)
  - Green, Valentine (1739-1813), after Edward Penny, The profligate punished by neglect and contempt, London, 1775, (mezzotint) (Box 3)
  - Guttenberg after Salvador Rosa, Tobie et Azarias, Paris, circa 1845, (lithograph) (Box 3)
  - Hénault, Jules, Le gourmand puni, Paris, circa 1885, (color lithograph) (Box 1)
  - Langlumé, L'indigestion from Album Comique, Paris, 1823, (color lithograph) (Box 1)
  - Lavrate, Je vous entends deja dire. Messieurs, cet homme est un saltimbanque, un charlatan..., Paris, 1884 [satire], (color lithograph) (Box 2)
  - Le Grand, Le trésors de l'alchimie, Paris, circa 1790, (engraving) (Box 2)
  - Lyonel, Paul, Assassinat du pharmacien de Limours, Paris, 1907, (color lithograph) (Box 2)
  - Maleuvre, La ribotte, à nos santés, Paris, 1823 [satire], (color lithograph) (Box 1)
  - Malteste, Le secret du docteur, Paris, circa 1885, (color lithograph) (Box 1)
  - Melling, after Salathé, Termes Marie Thérèse, Paris, circa 1850 (Box 3)
  - Meyer, H., Les victimes du devoir, France, 1888, (lithograph) (Box 3)
  - Piringer after Mellings, Éstablissement thermal de Rallière, Paris, circa 1850, (color lithograph) (Box 3)
  - Porter, A joint motion or the honeymoon of the coalition, London, 1783, (engraving) (Box 2)
  - Raffei, La peste, Paris, circa 1845, (lithograph) (Box 1)
  - Smillie, James, Portrait of William Osler before letters, U.S., circa 1923, (engraving) (Box 1)